whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases so I'm so glad you're
both joining me here for this and I have
a sense of how to proceed here and the
first thing I had asked we do is that we
take 30 seconds of silence together and
after that silence I'm going to open a
space as it were I have a sense perhaps
of what a link one of many between us is
and I would presence that and not put
that link or that frame before being
here now together more as a departure
point and we'll see where we land and
then we are then we are off so if that
sounds good then perhaps we can take 30
seconds of silence here I'm going to
shut my eyes please feel free to do
whatever is most natural yeah I will do
the same okay
oh so it is a a real pleasure in an
uncertain time to be here with you both
over the last four to five months I've
had the privilege of speaking with both
of you separately on a few Cape on a few
occasions each now and both of those
conversations have been deeply
meaningful to me and meaningful to many
I know who have listened and perhaps
even transformative for me and and my
sense is the wisdom inherent in the
embodiment I have been present to in
each of you as well as in the theory
that each of you have been developing on
and Express is one that is in an
important sense deeply resonant and well
worth present seeing together although
of course I don't just mean theory so my
hope is that in this conversation we can
all of get to know each other and
generate insight informative of you
understanding that is beneficial and
helpful really up and down the stack for
for for ourselves each other others and
not in any way disconnected from from
mind and heart and soul and what have
you and the sense I have of and here
I'll present something that is as well
core to the core insight that is moving
me and driving me to express and I
realize things in the world in
conformity with or being informed by is
the following and perhaps we can take
that as a departure point and that is
this
dynamic of the relationship between
authentic expression and how it is met
in relationship in its context and here
I'm going to use words that I know are
resonant with each of you in perhaps
slightly different ways but to that end
hopefully bring our vocabulary and sense
together in the expression of
authenticity when it is met in an
environment of care and perhaps a few
other things although I don't want to
belabor us with too many words when
authentic expression is met with care we
have here a core dynamic of the of the
dynamic of growth and when authentic
expression is truncated perhaps
traumatized we have here the the
opposite we have here the retraction of
the opportunity for growth in the
extreme and there's links here with this
with notions of voluntary confrontation
you know of a fear of uncertainty and we
have here also notions of the value of
stepping into vulnerability we also
presencing the importance of
relationship and this dynamic between
individual and context and self and
other so i from here as a framing I see
this as being something important to all
of us and deeply informative of the of
the ideas and ultimately embodied way we
might
realize in our lives and together and
I'm interested in how that lands for
both of you so that's that's all I have
to say powerful framing I guess I would
say I'd want to pull out two of the
central things that were sort of anchor
points on what you said this idea of
authentic dialogue authentic discourse
and part of what I would like to explore
is the possibility of opening both of
those back up putting them into question
and you know in a high to garyun sense
what do we mean by authenticity I think
it's I mean Heidegger is perhaps the
person who made that you know a way of
speaking
and but I imagine it has drifted quite
away from what it could be for us I'd
like to what I'm saying is I want to
open these both up in a reciprocal
questioning what do we mean what are we
trying to get at when we're trying to
get out of anticipating dialogue or what
I'd like to call deal logos and how do
those two opening up how do they relate
to each other because I think you're
right there's a there's people are at
least the people I'm coming into
communication with people are hungry for
a kind of connectedness that
simultaneously grounds them and affords
them also growth and transformation they
have a there's a hunger for this but
they feel that a lot of the ways the
terms and the concepts they bring to
bear to try and express it are not
translating into transformative practice
and so there seems to me to be a gap
between the conceptual framework we're
using to try and express this and the
ability to achieve the goals that we're
pursuing in the expression so that's
kind of what I'm interested in in this
framing
I guess what comes up for me right away
around that is this the paradoxes of of
where actually is the self so I'm
assuming that there's if we're gonna be
starting with this notion of
authenticity that we would be tapping
into something that was something
sincerely within me that I could share
with you and the paradox there is that
that I know of course I would offer you
everything I would gladly unzip myself
and be there but I have this this kind
of interesting tension of recognizing
that if I did what you would see is all
the ways in which the context that I
have lived with in the experiences that
I have had the the you know the traumas
from school and being wrong and the the
way in which you know maybe right now
our speech patterns are getting judged
that those would be indications and they
would be they would be an illustration
of all the ways in which that thing that
I would wish to unzip and show you that
would be truly mine is actually of the
context that I have been in and I
honestly have no idea how to tell the
difference I would like to be able to
say and Here I am in my most authentic
self what the heck is that and how could
I possibly extract that or find this
this nugget or essence even
because I think there is a kind of
yearning to get out that essence that is
somehow untouched by my culture my
experience my my my life my ancestors
life my you know my children's lives my
and I think especially right now in this
moment where there's so much melting in
the structures around us that this is a
question that bears a lot of
consideration around if I am shaped and
formed and forged in the the various
structures that I have lived within Who
am I when those structures are gone I
think that's really important how what I
understanding is saying and of course
please interject if I miss from you but
there is I think you're doing part of
what I wanted to do which is the
automaticity by which authenticity is
understood in terms of a reconnection
with one's inner true self is very is
very much the thing I want to bring into
question and that assumed idea that we
have this tables for the Cartesian
subjectivity within us that that is the
ultimate normative guide for our entire
life is precisely the thing peridot not
paradoxically ironically which was
Heidegger introduced the term
authenticity to try and call all that
into question and now it has somehow
circled around it is somehow circled
around their authenticity is if that
shows you how pervasive almost parasitic
that that that formulation of thinking
we want to call it the question is how
it can take something that was so
carefully crafted to call it into
question and absorb it back into itself
and say no no this is what it means and
this is what we've always been talking
about I I find that for something that
we should also just step back and pause
on right away and say notice how this
how the very thing was supposed to
challenge
all of this got reabsorbed into the very
machinery it was trying to challenge I
think that's that should give us some
pause for how carefully we need to work
together on this right now because
there's a lot happening in our cultural
coordinate Graham in our background
that's going to keep driving us back
towards that the very thing it's gonna
drive us towards a closure the very
thing we're trying to bring into
question but I hope I understood you
Nora because that's what that's the
connection I'm getting from what you
said that's that's exactly where I want
to go and I mean even language and
certainly communication patterns become
a kind of reflection of repetition of
extension of these various contextual
threads that say this is who I am this
is and when I want to say yeah but this
is the real me where's the real me and I
think that that there have been moments
and I think those moments of confusion
might be something really to look into
and that those moments where I prior to
the past couple of weeks my most
frequent experience of moments of
confusion that maybe had something of
that
what do I even want to call it is it's
something raw okay I'll just say it's
something wrong so it is when I live in
in Sweden and I live in I do a lot of a
lot of my life in multiple cultures and
so I mean Rana which is inherently a
multicultural place very multicultural
place please go ahead
yeah so one of the things that can
happen is that you I have found that I
could think that I have expressed
something and and then realized that
that is not what was received and get
very kind of disoriented in the
reception in the way the reception is
reflected back to me and and there's a
something that happens there that is is
like a crack in the matrix of my various
contextual formations and language and
and those cracks those cracks might be
the closest I know to to getting at this
thing and and and right now I think
there's an awful lot of cracks of
looking around and thinking you know
really who who are we what what do I say
what can we possibly say in this moment
being is authentic and the second I try
to make it authentic
it becomes hinting for sure yeah I
understand but that was a good point you
made about how you know the pattern that
I was pointing to sort of historically
with Heidegger is also something we find
prevalent in our own attempts IIIi was
what called to mind was a Leonard Cohen
song and he talks about you know the
crack that lets you know that lets the
light in yeah and so this leads me to
that this leads me to well somebody who
practiced introducing those cracks as a
way of trying to provoke wonder and I'd
like to at some point talk about the
difference between wonder which calls
this self and the world into question
and curiosity which tries to feed and
plug up the gaps in the self and and the
worldview and so but I'm so and and had
a lot to say about a biological notion
of the self and I'm thinking here of the
figure of Socrates that I'm and somebody
I'm working to try and understand very
deeply precisely because he had a form
of communicative practice that centered
upon introducing those cracks getting
people to a place of aporia where it was
possible it was not inevitable not
inevitable but it was possible for them
to come to a state of wonder that
opening where they could call that the
self and the world into question and
then they and that could induce them to
see the self as something that is
aspired to as opposed to something that
has already possessed and so I'm very
interested in all of that and the
question and the work I've been doing
with Peter Lindbergh and guys Sen stark
and Chris Masters Pietro is is it
possible for us and I'm changing the
question slightly no I don't I hope
you'll be patient with me is it possible
for us to learn from that such that we
could be better able to pursue what
we're trying to pursue right now which
is getting some sense of how to move
towards deeper communication deeper
community in a way that people are
craving so that's for me how I'm trying
to think about this right now I'm trying
to think about it in terms of people
have managed in past to give us examples
and to be exemplars of how to do the
thing we're doing and what
it mean for us to learn from him well
first of all can we learn from them and
then what does it mean for us to learn
from them and how do we bring that about
[Applause]
10 are you there still yeah we'll have
to see how we do this is a bit of an
unlikely occurrence the internet hasn't
had any problems since I've moved into
this apartment I'm going to open the
door to the bedroom so we're getting our
own aporia here a lot of the cracks are
shining coming right now for us so
technology is the God that limps opening
the door to let the internet in this is
that's next level my friend internet in
you know yeah yeah yeah the sacrifice is
my girlfriend's extra a couple hours of
sleeping here so there has been a cost
to this door opening but does it
actually work to open the door to let
the internet look I mean I don't
understand how signals work but there
seems to be a physical world where there
are some interactions and that's the
level of madness by which I'm
approaching this environment but as far
as I'm concerned it may be possible at
least you know I care it's my favorite
thing all day yeah it's how I so called
my problems actually but please get
serious here and let's get to work hmm
all right so I was I was proposing a
model that we could consider for
somebody who regularly you like I said
he he crafted the virtue of inducing the
cracks in people the aporia which let
the light shine through of a new
possibility of self and also a new
possibility of world and
you know that's that's wonder as just
and I follow fuller and other people and
seeing wonder is very different from
mere mere curiosity and that ability to
induce wonder and to put the bring
people to a place
it wasn't inevitable but it was possible
where they could aspire to a different
self and a different world is is I think
a valuable example for us to consider
precisely because the the Socratic model
of authenticity is an aspirational model
the true self is not something you
possess and it's not something you
possess in distinction from others or
your world it's something that you
aspire to continually and never in any
kind of completion to an ongoing process
of mutual transformation and although
I'm not claiming we can get back that
would be anachronistic and and and
therefore fallacious to Socrates or the
Socratic world although there are some
very important similarities Socrates was
carrying out his practice while Athens
is literally under siege the whole city
is quarantined and there had been a
plague so his context is not that
different from ours in some important
ways I'm recommending that we that we
take a look at Socratic dialogue as a
way of perhaps speeding up the process
by which we can learn about how to
recover a relational sentence of self
and an operational sense of authenticity
perhaps that are urgently needed right
now
and then that's on and I propose that to
Nora and then she had something to say
about it um yeah I really love that
you're taking it to this place John
because this is kind of where I'm
working with all my hours and moments
and days and heart and soul right now
and I have been generating these
okay let's call them dialogues but
there's they're sort of I called them
warm data labs okay so the idea is that
there's an exploration of a complex
question with a number of people and
that exploration includes them starting
in small groups around various contexts
and then they move when they want to but
if I don't ring a bell and make a move
they go where they want when they want
and things get mixed up this is you know
back in the days when people could be in
the same room together so what I started
to witness happening with that was
really interesting because as people to
explore to question whether that
question is something like you know what
is health or what is identity or what is
authenticity could even be one look that
that becomes something that is very
swiftly revealed in the stories and the
inputs between the people as being
something that exists between the
contexts and between the people so it
started a liminal revealer and an
interdependency revealer and and and so
I guess where I'm going with that is
that the the more of those processes
that I have done and I've been doing
hundreds of them around the world the
more I I'm seeing how important it is
that that process of opening those
cracks of coming into that that wonder
is actually uh it's not to be done alone
no we actually need each other to
provide multiple description and by that
I don't just mean lots of perspectives I
also mean lots of textures of ways of
talking so it's not just my professional
knowledge or or just my personal stories
right you have to have both of those and
questions and jokes and things that come
up between people that are unexpected
and that in a strange way in the the
most intimate kind of shiftings happen
in this possibility of having multiple
patterning 'he's kind of overlay like a
more a phenomenon mm-hmm so that in that
moiré a phenomenon there becomes I guess
one of the signatures of them soiree is
that you have one pattern and then you
have another pattern and when you cross
them you have a third pattern and that
third pattern can actually tell you
something about either of the other
patterns but it is this pet right and so
what I'm getting at is that a kind of
insight can come out of that overlay and
and so this is where where those
insights are not actually accessible
very often in life and in this moment
I'm with you there's an urgency so this
process that I've been playing with is
actually kind of an accelerated an
accelerated interdependency
insite maker that's great that's amazing
that's really cool it's really cool yeah
I'm very excited about this so I could
unpack this just a little that the
practice I don't know how much you know
of my work but I've been engaging in a
lot of participant observation and a lot
of these emerging I call them psycho
technologies or these practices of
trying to afford insight and flow within
you know within dialog within you know
distributed cognition and so it's really
you know and also people trying to put
things together
it's what I'm saying is there's this
interesting convergence or for example
I've been participating in circling and
then they're they're trying to get
circling to integrate with you know
bringing in important topical questions
so how do we go from just circling where
we're maintaining the circle to making
it topical in a fashion and and then
what are the bridging processes you do
because if you just sort of slam people
from circling to a topic they can get
sort of it can the coherence can break
and so I'm it's really interesting about
how a lot of things seem to be coming
you know towards each other so I can I
ask you some more
I don't know this isn't the right
adjective so but be forgiving on it can
I ask you some more technical questions
more specific questions about so sorry
this is what I'm just gonna be a little
bit of a cognitive scientist here for a
moment because I'm really really
intriguing this one thing and and and
this is something that pattern my pipe
I'm not trying to take anything away for
you I've thought about doing that
because that's very similar about you
know this sort of small world network
formation you get within a brain to
provoke insight with in effort and I was
wondering if we could get that sort of
fluid small world network restructuring
between people that would also bring
about an insight and it seems like
you've actually already cottoned onto
this and made it work so that is that is
really fascinating and then I'm what I'm
really interested in well there's
multiple things use what you said is
just lighting me up right now I
interested in the what's the
relationship between you know the group
insight if you and the individual
insights how are they resonating with
each other how is that working and then
the thing you talked about with the
patterns so Chris and I talked about
that in the article the chapter we've
written about this sort of third factor
that emerges I see it encircling all the
time in which you get you get so you'll
get people who get into this like two
people than these people and then that
gets late and you get that emergent this
what we call the third factor I can give
it sort of an extensive reference
without a very just clear denotation and
I'm real and what's interesting is
people's I I want to ask you if this is
also the huh
like do people sense that but do they
get a sense of something telling them or
calling them to move from one one of the
groups to another and do they get a
sense of you know that something is
taking shape like a like that has a sort
of a systemic life of its own above and
beyond not only the individuals but the
subgroup because I'm definitely finding
that you know reported continuously when
I'm doing the participant observation of
these other kinds of practices is that
is that also going on in the one-day to
lab absolutely and and one of the things
that happens is that it it I mean I I
did a lot of systems teaching and
complexity teaching and it was frankly
irritating because you know II people
would come and we'd have these great
workshops and people who understood it
before felt very clever and the people
who didn't understand it
maybe had a little sense of it for a
little while but then it would kind of
fade away with ether away from them and
a here's what I'm finding is that there
the the structure of the process has to
do with creating the opportunities for
about so that people can have a
conversation about the question of what
is health through the context of economy
and then they can move over to family
and and in those little circles they
tell all sorts of stories and all kinds
of
stuff you there's absolutely no
conscious purpose control over what gets
talked about there's no documentation
very important no documentation what do
you mean specifically by that it's not
recorded or people aren't allowed to
cite stuff
what does that mean I usually don't do
either okay okay there's no post-its
there's no paper tablecloths there's
nobody writing anything down because
those contextual interactions the story
that you tell me about your grandmother
recipe reminds me of something and that
is a link like compost finding links
finding relational process right and so
that that is and then I go to another
context and someone says something and
it connects then to your grandmother's
story and the memory that that brought
me to and so that this understanding of
if you want to call it systemics or
complexity or inter dependency whatever
you want to call that it turns out to be
very intimate so is the idea that there
there there exemplifying it now right
there instantiate it they're
participating in it they're not just
sort of talking about it yeah well
what's happening is there's an about and
there's a within ah right right so the
the conditions of the lab are structured
to offer the space for people to talk
about right but in the negative space of
it
there's the liminal of what's actually
connecting in the within so you never
have a warm data lab on relationships or
communication because that would be
ridiculous those are all things that are
forming in the within yeah right so so
that's been really interesting and then
after the lab there's this moment that I
would call the mutual learning moment so
then there's a sort of a moment when we
have the room in plenary
and say so you know what did you notice
what have you observed and that's when
you get that group lift but most of them
don't actually have words for what
they've experienced because it's been
such a combination of intellectual and
physical and emotional and memory and
all these things have been kind of
mushing and reconnecting and they're in
a territory they've never actually had
to make words for before hmm but a
couple of people in the room will find
the words and when they start to find
the words the other people also find
words and the words are usually
something along the lines of I started
to notice that I you know there was
repeated things in multiple contacts
that there was overlap that when I left
one context the conversation that I had
there didn't go out of my body I took it
with me it was season two the next
conversation and so you get this lift
that happens in that moment where the
whole room realizes that they've had
very different experiences but they've
had a they've had a mutual learning at
the same time so this idea that mutual
learning doesn't mean we're learning the
same thing look it means we're learning
together and that that is as unique for
you or me or you know anybody of any age
and and really I've been working with
this in very vulnerable communities and
also in Parliament's so in inner-city
Pittsburgh with groups of Islamic women
in Asia in really broken towns in the UK
and then with the Finnish politicians or
with so it's really it kind of anyone
can do it kids can do it for sure yeah
it's pretty interesting so have you has
it's been written down anywhere or have
you liked because I'd like to learn more
about it and we have limited time here
maybe you and I can I mean how does one
learn to practice it because come on
take our now so it's it's a it's there's
a lot of theory there and so to bring
this kind of back to where we are with
this conversation I think probably one
of the most important pieces is the
piece around abductive process and and
that that is the piece where it starts
to become clear in this question of of
authenticity that there is a kind of
cross contextual description that we
live within everyone lives within it in
fact I would say probably every living
thing lives within a cross contextual
description so if you look at an
earthworm that earthworm is a
description in a way of the soil it's
also a description of the tree or of the
bird or of the grandpa and grandson that
are going to go fishing or right so that
earthworm is is just like you and I are
a description of our education system
we're a description of our culture we're
and in these different contexts are
difficult to grab hold of and fix
in isolation are in reductionism because
they're actually not where they you grab
them and they're not there you want to
fix the education system but it's
actually it's actually creative in the
abductive process of our economy and
culture and intergenerational
expectations and identity and you know
all these things good then you know the
education system is a consequence right
right
I see here John if if I can just to know
we are track do it no no no no no no no
no not at all
just to draw some things together and
make sure that I'm up and with this and
also perhaps is to add a little bit so
if I can synthesize sort of some of the
themes we've we've touched on so far and
importantly authenticity is not the the
expression or the capturing of something
that is the inherent and importantly
fixed to you but something that is
realized in a some form of cooperative
but ultimately interdependent dynamic on
an ongoing basis with each other so we
are we are present seeing from a
phenomenological perspective that we are
talking more than that a question might
be what is it to show up to
transformation to learning to the during
fourth and and remembering of engaging
in a remembering of what it is to be
with each other and also an aspiration
of our becoming and deepening together
too so what we can perhaps add in
although not to jump the gun is what are
some of these modes of orientation and
this is something I've thought a lot
about what are ways we show up actually
to these moments of when the moment is
upon us
John you like to use this term Kairos
that there is a significant imminence to
the now where we
maybe particularly challenged or call up
called upon to presence ourselves in an
appropriate or right relationship with
each other given the given a kind of
particular energetic context thrust upon
us and it seems to me we if we really
were to not be reductive but but attempt
to synthesize some core modes we might
take in response to this we can we can
allow ourselves to be moved by this
process in a way that's appropriate and
we can allow ourselves as well to more
confront and move this process too so
there's a sort of a push and pull
dynamic that can be done effectively or
less effectively and a lot of that I
think has to do with how well we are
able to sense what is the appropriate
ripening vulnerability to step into with
a certain kind of care and courage
rather than to rather than to either
bury our heads when faced with a moment
or in fact to attempt to close that
opening before in fact we were able to
find and be with each other in order to
then come to some kind of harmony or
movement together so and I think this
can help ground us as well back in what
some of the experiences are we're having
in our lives at the moments because fear
of course is very much heightened and
care and courage are very much called
for in this time and it is my hope in a
deeper sense that the kind of theory we
might be discussing in this conversation
is in actual fact a crucial piece at
more than a crucial piece that all of
this together is very much involved in
the movement towards the realization of
we because that is also what we are
discussing here how can we create these
mutual learning environments where we
can give and receive to our fullest as
best we can informative and enabling of
transformation both individually and
collectively in touch with ecology so
grounding this back in our moment today
I think is important because the
emotionality people
experiencing and attention they're
experiencing in their lives
I think we're Altima are making calls
here that there are a call for stepping
into that moment holding oneself in such
a way that enna enables us to transform
that toward a wholeness not a final one
Whitehead has this expression the many
become one and are increased by one
which is a process framing of some of
what we are discussing here so to add
some of these pieces in am I sort of on
track with some of the core features of
our discussion I think so I I mean
there's two things I guess I'd want to
say first to respond to you and then to
threat back to Panora I think what we're
talking about here in the thing in I
mean there's like I see this as a
feature of many of these emerging
practices there's this oscillation
between theory and theory aware I mean
using theory in the old sense of the
word you know the contemplative
immersive involvement that you know
gives you insight and then there's
reflective theory that that movement is
and trying to figure out what some of
those patterns are not just for theories
sake
because I think what what Nora is doing
and you know what guys doing the
circling I'd like what Nora's doing
though because it's got this topical
element to it that I think is really
important in central and it's got this
ability it's got its got a grammar built
in of of you know explicit restructuring
and the way people move around and I
think these are important things to take
note of and that's why I was taking note
of them but towards your question Tim is
that these practices give people a deep
taste what I call a participatory in
perspective of knowing of the power and
the potential of you know of our I don't
like this term and but it's you know of
our sense making and our meaning making
capacities with people the thing people
will take significant hits to their
standard of living
if they get a sense a you know a felt
sense of a course of mattering a course
of the enhanced connectedness that's why
people have children I mean it having a
child is completely irrational from a
subjective point of view as your health
goes down your finances go down you're
tired all the time your most significant
relationship is is put into Christ like
every all of your subjective well-being
just crashes when you have a child you
ask people why they do it they do it
because they want it they feel connected
and involved with and involved with not
just theorizing about they feel
participatory
in the creation of something that
transcends them in an important way so
giving people if you can give these
practices have a value I would argue in
helping people remember in you know in
in a sense of sati right mindfulness
deeply remember you know and I want to
use this taste metaphor like in the
Bible you know taste the Lord and see
that he is good but they can they can
remember what this is like what it's
like to be immersed in this to flow with
this and I think that gives people a
kind of faith encourage that is deeply
realizable and relevant right here right
now that's so yes I'm getting the
nerdish scientist and I'm really excited
and interested about what Noor is
talking about you know as a scientist
but I think I can make I think I just
made it there's a case for this the
existential import of what we're
discussing I think is also apparent and
should be should be noted
that's one that's how I would response
year that sort of reframing I think they
here I think we're there is we have we
can have a kind of stereoscopic vision
where the the theoretical concern and
the existential concern are both
actually being fused into a kind of
depth in which that is a value to us
right here right now hmm well that seems
to be called for in this time and I
wonder if the framing of the concepts of
the interior and the exterior is part of
what is may be helpful to presence here
as well so core to how I've been one way
I've been attempting to communicate the
project I've been on with this for some
years is to and I'm not like I'm not
happy with this framing necessarily
there's other things I would prefer to
say but what I have been saying
explicitly in places is the process of
making sense of what to care about and
of course it's more like caring about
making sense of what to care about but
there's because there's this there's a
sense in which these things are so
interdependent yet there is an
orientation towards I think ultimately
grounded in something like of love and
for love that's I think better made
better related to in a language of
perhaps care or towards that
metaphorical way rather than sense but
we are here in this moment together
where so much is shifting and it's how
can we draw in what is most relevant and
also be anchored in what is what is most
worth caring about
and so it's bringing these two together
in the process absolutely that seems to
be so fundamental well I mean that's
Socrates taught erotica
Socrates knew how to care and that's a
central idea in Heidegger like the the
the the the you know the wisdom of
caring well and you know that's where I
think and I want to turn it back to Nora
now that's what I think the work I do on
relevance realization seems to line up I
think I have a sense I'm not clear yet
but it seems at least it's convergent
with what she stopped talking about when
she's talking about
sort of this abductive process that's at
work because that comes up a lot in in
in in my work too and so I want to turn
back to Nora and I want to hear more
about this abductive process mmm yeah
the abductive process is really
interesting because I'm pretty sure that
that's where the change actually is and
it's something that is is largely
missing from most of the diagrams of and
explanations of systems change there's
it's actually in the abductive process
that you're going to get the real shift
and and that's really I would say in in
my sort of verbage around this that's a
very trans contextual yeah it's
happening across them through multiple
contexts and it requires that and we do
it all the time anyway it's just a
matter of allowing for a different
abductive process so if if I'm in an
abductive process where my identity is
formed through and across the various
institutions of our world my education
my job my family my wealth my economy my
health my sexuality my gender my right
all of these things and and and all of
them are describing each other that's
that's the piece that when it when you
get it it's like oh that's there it is
but it's a little tricky to do in a you
know 40 minute podcast but the thing is
is that in there there is another kind
of integrity so when when I'm seeing
abductive shift in groups with groups of
people I don't guide it know I just make
a space for it and this is actually
critical I don't ever ever make any
inclination of what I think people
should learn or could come out the other
end of this thinking because I feel like
that is absolutely not my territory I
can make a space for those connections
to happen but they should be alive they
should be as complex and as unique as
every person in that room with infinite
possibilities of connecting their ideas
and stories and inputs so it's it's very
alive and that living thing is totally
unpredictable at the same time it's
pretty predictable every time I've done
it there's been a shift um and so I just
don't know what the details of that
shift are I don't get to voice or shape
or define or in any way describe that
shift I can only make a space for it so
what people are able to do when they
start to move across those contexts as
they can see the way in which they are
interdependent and that perception
without any effort has the second-order
response of a kind of integrity it has
to do with recognizing not integrity
around what's right or wrong but
integrity to show up and respond in ways
that are inclusive of that
interdependence II as opposed to just
looking at one one sort of solution in
one context at a time or or one one
trauma in one context at a time you know
so often trauma gets put into really
reductionist terms and so there's a kind
of a therapeutic and a healing quality
to this that is I think what we're
talking about when we say people are
longing this connection that in in that
longing what happens is
that when you start to see that this
thing that is a trauma that you might be
carrying is not actually it's not
actually located in any particular
context it's moving between all of them
and other people are sharing other
traumas that are woven between all these
different contexts and suddenly that
trauma isn't as internal it becomes
something that is a perceivably
contextual and trans contextual which is
an enormous relief and when I say it's
warm data it's it's like literally warm
you can literally feel the warmth of
that so it's it's interesting to see
that and especially in this moment which
i think is a moment of a need for a
completely it's a need to integrate in
another way so how do we begin to create
the conditions for people to integrate
together into a way of seeing and and
responding to this time I think that's
an excellent question and I'm
particularly interested in one aspect of
that question that I alluded to or I
mentioned earlier which is I'm
interested in what are the conditions
that afford insight for people and how
those interact with what are those what
are the conditions that afford insight
between people and how and then there's
kind of a third thing what is the what
is for the optimal relationship between
the the the individual insight and the
collective insight and that's something
I'm trying to get a deeper understanding
of IIIi think
the fact that people are enacting and
literally moving and they're embodying
the interdependence I think that is
probably playing a very significant role
in in the practice because you know
you're triggering the cerebellum you're
getting people to literally reorient
their visual processing what they're
foregrounding and back rounding is
literally shifting we know that those
kinds of processes trigger individual
insight and then if they're and if that
if that's an insight that also you know
gets them to realize the interdependence
then I can see how the groups would also
restructure collectively so that various
things are again being facilitated it's
interesting about this maybe I can form
a question around that bridge that I
just made because when you look within
individual cognition inducing
criticality you have to introduce some
significant amount of disruption like if
if you hear somebody's trying to solve
an insight problem on a computer screen
you put some static or some noise and it
put a bit of entropy in it or you allow
or or you moderately distract them not
to distracted so they leave the problem
but enough that they'll sort of you know
they get you break up the stability and
that criticality actually affords the
restructuring like the way a sand pile
will self organize and then it
avalanches and that affords a new
structure so I'm wondering if if if you
if you see that playing a role within
the one data that there's there's you
know there's there's there's there's is
there a presence of disruptive
strategies sort of being played with you
know in contrast but interdependently
with constructive strategies you're
seeing that the criticality and the
construction are sort of usually
interpenetrating is that happening
absolutely because when people go into
so if you get up from one context and
you walk over to another one noise
induction yeah yeah right you you have
to actually you know come into that so
there's a lot of what's happening who's
here there's a whole process of paying
attention in ways
are all sorts of nonverbal attention and
then in engaging in that conversation
and bringing with you this conversation
that just came onboard and maybe the one
before that because it's usually the
third context that you start to get the
the pop yeah that makes sense to me and
it's it's also being in a room where
there are all those contexts so you have
you're in a room where there is this
meta right and that people can hear it
in the background to some degree right
that's right yeah and so that you don't
get to forget that you're in this meta
which is really interesting it it
actually it really decreases the
possibility for polarization which is
really really interesting especially in
you know in these times where there's
been so much polarization that you know
usually we go traveling down a rabbit
hole because we feel like there's some
context someone's not seeing and but if
it's in the room and it's just over
there you can just go over there it's
not people are less prone to positioning
yeah so there's that and that is I guess
you could call that a disruptor but it's
a gentle one yeah I think I mean you
want wild it's also you know you don't
want to you don't want to break the
system right now you've got to perturb
it because if you don't perturb it
enough it you know it'll get into a
local minima it'll stabilize prematurely
and then people can often not you know
explore this the space of possibilities
as deeply as as is probably needed and
the other thing is that I think that you
talked about topics yeah and one of the
things that is really important is to
not have topics where people have
scripts so that's an interesting
question how do you do that because you
know a lot of the a lot of the things
you brought up as examples struck me as
one which people often have
you know pretty firm opinions that have
a lot of cultural baggage of touch them
like health for example like you know
people have lots of opinions about
health of course now even more so and
there's all this cultural valuation of
health han says you know that health has
become our God in some ways it's
whatever it's the thing that justifies
everything else we do so what does that
mean that that's very provocative what
you just said how would you bring up
like that existed let's do that one
because it's actually relevant to how
would you bring up health and keep it
off script how does that work well you
might bring up family hmm okay if I was
working with a bunch of doctors but I
might bring use family health be one of
the contexts I see I see I see so that
you get this right you get it off center
so that you can actually reorient and
read that the abductive processes move
in other ways oh that's very good
that's very good yeah because
decentering strategies also are things
found within individual cognition and
insight so it's interesting of that
murren that's really cool
I had one recently and and this I think
Tim this really is important with your
question around authenticity because
this is this is kind of critical is how
to get off of these scripts and the
scripts have meaning and have have have
have a set of signaling and receiving
possibilities within relationships if
you if you are in a set of different
relationships those signaling
don't go anywhere you can still signal
they just kind of dud so it's it's
something to get off context too if you
have a bunch of you know doctors talking
about media for example
and family and suddenly that there's all
kinds of health stuff that is implicit
in there and it connects in but it isn't
what they're saying so it's this thing
of not going for the direct corrective
which is going to generate all sorts of
reductionist scripted maybe I don't know
how that connects to authenticity but I
know that when people don't know what
they're gonna say and they haven't said
that thing before and they weren't
considering the the thing that was going
to come from the person that just said a
thing that that they they enter into a
discourse in another way they enter into
a mutual learning in a way that
surprises even them but I think that's
excellent connection to authenticity
Nora I mean there's a deep connection
between getting off script and what
we're trying to do here I mean right it
is in this discussion about authenticity
is we're trying to get I mean there's
kind of a metal level we're trying to
get off script about authenticity and
it's now it's now that well part of what
this attempt to reformulate authenticity
is is centering on is the very capacity
and ability to get off script but do it
like you said you have to do it in this
to do it you know you have to do it in a
certain way you have to pick you have to
get it like if it's health and you go
off center because you actually talked
about family you wouldn't talk about
like elephants for example right you
it's about it's you've got it like so
there's finesse in the sense that
there's finesse in this if you know I'm
a Tai Chi player and there's this sense
about you know a can you can you pick up
on the grain of things and follow the
grain and and get a sense of how you
know well you know you're sparring with
somebody as you said you know you don't
just hit them cuz that they'll just
flock but can you get them off center
and then there's possibilities that open
up and so I think I think I like what
you just said I like this idea about a
connection between reconceptualization
perhaps of authenticity by connecting it
to getting people off script
in you know in a way that shows finesse
and affords inside it I think that's a
very I think that's very powerfully
connected to what we're talking about
with authenticity yeah that all of this
rings very true and
there's some things I can presence here
that I think are vital and I supposed to
go metal on it the turn is for me to
speak personally the reason for that is
when we drop into the personal and move
towards where we are vulnerable this has
an effect on
getting the context within which other
participants may or may not be willing
to go and so here why John you you
reference finesse because of course
there are the three of us here but there
are also more than the three of us here
at least potentially and this is very
significant and this is an obstacle not
an obstacle without it's an opportunity
but an obstacle we all here
face this notion of off-script is
something that has had much resonance
with me for a long time I in fact set up
an event last year
I hired out a theater and the event was
called off script and I attempted to
have people come along to that event but
I cancelled it because I could not get
anyone to come so the question is how
then do you invite a setting where we
really can't go off script because the
price is high the price of admission is
much higher than a ticket because really
if we were to open up again to the
significance we are here a part of this
moment we are in in the world the
vulnerability there the confrontation
with death and perhaps worse that is
there the various ways in which we may
or may not have been seen with each
other in this on this ride towards that
which we perceive as perhaps ending and
in suffering I think all magnifies each
other and so
yes things are about going off-script
and they always have been and whether or
not we were aware of it part of us
always was we just lost awareness of it
even as we ran out certain programs and
mistook perhaps programs for the
totality but there are it seems to me
things we can't stand on and ground
ourselves on even though that is not a
fixed ground they are certain
imperatives that we can or cannot accept
a covenant if you like we can enter into
of course all things can be broken but
there are consequences to those to that
breaking and so as we are here
attempting to understand what is a for
dn't of authenticity and what is a for
dn't of or the presencing of
authenticity in relationship as amiable
to a reciprocal opening and this
abductive process of understanding we
one thing I think can be put forward is
that a commitment to be here now
together at least for a certain duration
knowing that cutting the duration itself
is already limiting the context if we
take that to be truly what we are doing
so what does it mean to then truly
commit to being here with each other and
just how much are we able to integrate
through that process even as someone
drops into the space with the context
shifting and psyche unsettling and chaos
inducing fluxes apparitions of the
vulnerability of our existential
predicament both now and perhaps also
eternally
to really step in is not a flippant one
and this I suppose is not a bad place
for me to for me to stop this and see if
this is landed I it strikes me that what
what what you're talking about is a kind
of rigor and that it's a rigor that I I
have so much fection
for because it's it's a rigor for
perceiving and looking for maybe with
that wonder that you were speaking of
earlier John you know interdependency is
a lot of differences a lot of vitality a
lot of interactions a lot of relational
messiness and it's not to be
underestimated
the kind of the kind of multi sensory
perception that it takes to pay
attention in that way and so it's you
know it's not as if you can just do
complexity as an intellectual game
right it's if you don't allow that
complexity to be perceived through your
own complexity that is not just in words
or jargons or maps but also in stories
and music and unspoken sensed things and
all kinds of other information that's
there you need all of it if you're gonna
enter into that integrity or that
authenticity it's a kind of alertness in
the rigor and so I guess that's what I'm
kind of hearing you say right off the
bat what do you think John what are you
hearing well I'm hearing something
similar to that and overlaps with it and
I'm hearing the commitment and I like
the notion of rigor I'm hearing that
noir that you're you talk about things I
used the language of kind of knowing
that are not propositional there's
procedural knowing and respect travel
and participatory and I think what
you're saying is the knowing and I'm
using knowing that knowledge
deliberately knowing of complexity is
something we only know within and
through our own complexity right it's
it's a participatory knowing it's not
just a referential knowing and I think
that's really important and so I'm
hearing that the commitment therefore is
a kind of comprehensive commitment to I
like this notion of rigor
about trying to bring I well let me let
me try it this way what I heard when I
heard that rigor and that you took it to
those deep levels in response to Tim
he's like I said I'm hearing I'm hearing
virtue I'm hearing I'm hearing that
we're virtue doesn't mean the possession
of a rule we reduced virtue which were
it originally meant they sort of person
hole capacity and power for D
with you know the the messy ill-defined
situations of life and then we reduced
it to the possessions of sets of rules
and you know and you know sort of
content procedures and I think that's
why the Aristotelian model of the virtue
that's kind of something that's always
found between different kinds of vices
vices of defect and vices of excess and
so it's it's a virtue is more like a
virtual engine it
it's what constantly steers you between
the vicissitudes of a self-organizing
process so you don't fall out of it
that's and that's what I hear Tim saying
is is needed that people that come into
these the intention to commit is
necessary but nowhere sufficient for
being able to commit you need particular
skills and virtues in order to commit in
the way we're talking about here now I
don't want to I don't want to build a
you know a catch-22 in here I think with
the practice that Nora is talking about
is a way in which people can start to
cultivate of these virtues but I think
to meet the normative demand that Tim is
talking about I think we do need to talk
about virtue at some point that these
practices should result in people
carrying away in their person not
beliefs but carrying away skills and
virtues that transfer into multiple
contexts in your life and I you know I
think the meta virtue of course is
wisdom and so I that's what I think is
the normativity that I heard you
pointing towards Tim and I think when
you can when people can realize and I
mean that in both senses of the word
come to awareness and make real when
people can realize that these practices
our affording deeply affording of the
cultivation of connectedness and the
virtues that would properly how's that
and and guide it
I think that's deeply motivating to
people I think that's deeply motivating
to people I think that goes back towards
you know giving them a taste
but a taste of the good if you'll allow
me a platonic word and you know what you
know what Nora was talking about sounded
so similar to me to what Iris Murdoch
talks about when she talks about the you
know the the the necessity for paying
you know to for a particular kind of
complex attention and she it's called
the sovereignty of the good for a reason
she she allies that capacity with the
ability to orient towards the good to
love the good to be tempted by the good
and I think when people get a taste for
this Tim that could really afford the
kind of commitment that you're talking
about that's what that's how that's what
I hear yes yes um can I ask how I just
think it appropriate here to just check
in and to be conscious of everyone's
time what are we looking at over the
next few minutes here I'm I had us down
to 5:30 so I I'm coming up I'm coming up
in sort of a heart yeah I'm soon I don't
want I mean I don't want to be
presumptive and I don't want a corner
Nora in any way or you Tim but I'm happy
to come back and to have another
discussion I found this one I'm
incredibly rich and you could tell at
times it was it was really getting me
quite impassioned in the good sense of
the word
thank you it's so nice to meet you so I
love this yeah long overdue what took us
so long I don't know the world
intervenes in our lives and ways right
that's happened so I I mean I'm pretty
much going to have to leave soon Tim but
Pete um I again I'm not making a demand
on anybody I'm just speaking for myself
I am committing if it is desired to do
one of these again I enjoyed this
thoroughly I think it's fruitful and
valuable and pertinent given where we're
at right now and so you know and it
doesn't have to be a long time from now
if if schedules permit and people are
willing and wanting you know a few weeks
from now and I'm happy to do this again
and pick up on these threads and going
yeah so I'm just saying that right here
right now
as a way of expressing my gratitude by
making a commitment yes I second that
sorry yeah grateful be honored well
thank you so much and as usual for me
with with so much with so much more to
say and in the acceptance at the time is
not now I will thank you so much for for
joining me this was for me an
opportunity and intention to bring
together two people that I find to be to
possess no no shortage of beauty and
wisdom together it's always a pleasure
to see you Tim and it's been a great
pleasure meeting and getting into
dialogue with you Nora and I look
forward to doing it again
I do too John and thank you so much Tim
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases